Finding Aid for the Herbert Wisbey, Jr. Papers
Elmira College
Finding Aid for the Herbert Wisbey, Jr. Papers
1907 - 2004
The papers document Herb Wisbey’s tenure as the Director of the Center of Mark Twain Studies at Elmira College from its inception in 1983 to 1986. The collection contains research materials for many of his published articles, primarily for those published in the Mark Twain Society Bulletin. Correspondence, Mark Twain research materials and a research file of predominantly local figures represent the extent of the collection.
3.33 Linear Ft. (8 manuscript boxes)
Wisbey, Herbert A. (Herbert Andrew), 1919-
Mark Twain Archive, Gannett-Tripp Library, Elmira College, Elmira, N.Y.
Unrestricted
Born in Boston, Massachusetts and raised in Rhode Island, Wisbey came to the Southern Tier Region of New York in 1952, taking a position as Head of the Department of History and Political Science at Keuka College. Dr. Herbert Wisbey received degrees from University of Rhode Island and the University of Arizona, earning a Ph.D from Columbia University in 1951. In 1962, Wisbey joined the faculty at Corning Community College and three years later he joined the faculty of Elmira College.
Dr. Wisbey served as Professor of American History and became the Archivist of Elmira College in 1974. He authored several books before co-writing Mark Twain in Elmira with Robert Jerome in 1977. In 1983, Wisbey became the first director of the Center for Mark Twain Studies following the gift of Quarry Farm by the Langdon family of Elmira. He retired from Elmira College in 1986, receiving Emeritus distinction.
Center for Mark Twain Studies
The Herbert Wisbey Papers document the formative years of the Center for Mark Twain Studies containing the Quarry Farm Advisory Board meeting minutes, correspondence, research and information on Quarry Farm, the summer home of Mark Twain. These materials provide a superficial glance of the history, collections and administration of the Center for Mark Twain Studies at the time of its inception, documenting the years 1983 to 1986.
- Series 1: Center For Mark Twain Studies and Mark Twain Society Bulletin materials, 1952 - 2004; This series has been arranged in alphabetical order by folder title and contains materials associated with Herb Wisbey’s tenure as director of the Center for Mark Twain Studies. Materials related to the Mark Twain Society Bulletin are also included.
  This series has been arranged in alphabetical order by folder title and contains materials associated with Herb Wisbey’s tenure as director of the Center for Mark Twain Studies. Materials related to the Mark Twain Society Bulletin are also included.
  - Advisory Board - Reports of the Quarry Farm Advisory Board and Director; National Trust for Historic Preservation documents, 1983 - 1986 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Advisory Board -- Board minutes, annual reports, memos, correspondence; including Center for Mark Twain Studies events and promotional materials, 1993 - 1996 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Copper Plate -- Mark Twain's 67th Birthday etching, correspondence concerning the item in the Mark Twain Archive, 1981 - 1993 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Correspondence -- Materials concerning the Center for Mark Twain Studies during Wisbey's tenure as director, 1983 - 1986
  - Cotton, Michelle -- Independent Study, "Mark Twain's Elmira" manuscript, 1986
  - Harnsberger, Caroline -- "Mark Twain, Craftsman" manuscript, 1980
  - Karanovich, Nick -- Correspondence, includes discussion of the Pond photographs donated to Elmira College from Nick Karanovich, 1985 - 1988
  - Lectures on Mark Twain -- Outlines and notes for lectures, 1984 - 1985
  - Mark Twain in Elmira -- Clippings, publication by Jervis Langdon, miscellaneous materials, 1975 - 1983
  - Mark Twain in Elmira -- Reviews, clippings and photographs of Wisbey and Jerome, 1977
  - Mark Twain Foundation -- Proposals, correspondence, 1982 - 1984
  - Mark Twain Papers -- Correspondence and research materials primarily concerning Mark Twain Letters, 1993 - 1994
  - Mark Twain Papers -- Primarily correspondence concerning research, 1990 - 1991
  - Mark Twain Society -- By-Laws, minutes, clippings, promotional materials, 1975 - 1988
  - Mark Twain Society Bulletin -- Article manuscripts, research materials, correspondence, 1980 - 1981
  - Mark Twain Society Bulletin -- Mal Marsden article not used, "Mark Twain and the Face of the Land" manuscript, undated
  - Mark Twain Society Bulletin, July 1996 -- Manuscripts and materials for publication
  - Mark Twain Society Bulletin, Jan 1997 -- Manuscripts and materials for publication, 1996 - 1997
  - Mark Twain Society Bulletin, July 1997 -- Manuscripts and materials for publication
  - National Register of Historic Places -- Elmira College Old Campus and Mark Twain Study correspondence and nomination form, 1985
  - News clippings -- Mark Twain related, 1992 - 1996
  - Proposal -- Biographical Twain series proposal by Sandra Bradley, 1993
  - Quarry Farm -- Clippings found in books, includes correspondence and photocopies of clippings, 1904 - 2004
  - Quarry Farm: Fireplace Tiles -- Research and manuscript by Barbara Taylor, includes notes, undated
  - Quarry Farm: History and Architecture -- Research materials, floor plans, correspondence, clippings, 1952 - 1975
  - Quarry Farm: Marginalia and miscellaneous materials from Quarry Farm -- Primarily photocopied letters, no materials concerning Mark Twain, undated
  - Reviews: Mary Boewe review of "Mark Twain in the Company of Women" by Laura Skandera Trombley -- Includes correspondence with Wisbey, 1995
  - Siena College Conference -- Includes correspondence, program and clipping; Jeffrey Steinbrink article, Mark Twain on the Mountaintop: The Elmira Connection; Richard Veler article, "Mark Twain: A Not-So-Innocent Abroad, 1985
  - Wharton, William -- Poems written at Quarry Farm from a visit in 1983, includes clipping about the author and poet, 1984
- Series 2: Correspondence, 1980 - 1997
  The bulk of this series includes collegial letters concerning research, publication and solicitation for reviews and articles for the Mark Twain Society Bulletin. The bulk of the letters are routine letters of transmittal and do not provide an in-depth look at scholarship or Wisbey’s personal or collegial relationships. This Series is arranged alphabetically by author’s last name or organizational name.
  - Boewe, Mary -- Correspondence, 1985 - 1997
  - Cobblestone Magazine -- Correspondence, 1983 - 1987
  - Grant, Leonard -- Correspondence, 1985 - 1986
  - Gribben, Alan -- Correspondence, 1980 - 1986
  - Keniston, Maxwell -- Correspondence, 1991 - 1995
  - Kiskis, Michael -- Correspondence, 1987 - 1992
  - Langdon, Jervis -- Correspondence, includes clippings, 1974 - 1997
  - Mark Twain Boyhood Home (Henry Sweets) -- Correspondence, includes promotional materials, 1983 - 1995
  - Mark Twain Memorial -- Correspondence and Newsletters, 1981 - 1997
  - Mark Twain Papers -- Correspondence, 1983 - 1995
  - Mark Twain Society Bulletin -- Correspondence, research materials, clippings and photographs used in publications, 1979 - 1995
  - Riegstad, Tom -- Correspondence, 1992 - 1993
  - Taylor, Barbara -- Correspondence, includes early history of Livy's education in Elmira, 1997
  - Tenney, Tom -- Correspondence, 1981 - 1997
- Series 3: Mark Twain research materials, 1953 - 1997
  This series is arranged alphabetically by folder title and is primarily comprised of notes and photocopied research materials. There are a number of miscellaneous folders are at the end of the series.
  - Mark Twain Autograph Prices -- Research materials, 1981 - 1994
  - Mark Twain Autographs -- photocopied letters of Mark Twain, undated
  - Mark Twain and Browning -- Research materials and photocopies, undated
  - Mark Twain Chronology -- Research materials and correspondence, 1987
  - Mark Twain Encyclopedia -- materials for inclusion, 1989 - 1993
  - Mark Twain Impersonators -- materials, 1980 - 1993
  - Mark Twain Memorial -- Photocopied materials, transcription of Charles Langdon's Journal, passport, and Jervis Langdon obituary, undated
  - Mark Twain Sayings -- Notes, clippings, research materials, undated
  - Mark Twain: Stomach Club address, 1601 photocopies, undated
  - Quarry Farm History -- compiled history of Quarry Farm including research materials, undated
  - The Twainian, 1993 - 1997
  - Young, Art -- Sketch of Twain, photocopy and correspondence, 1984
  - Miscellaneous: Good (1) -- Research materials, correspondence, 1953 - 1995
  - Miscellaneous (2) -- photocopied articles, undated
  - Miscellaneous (3)-- Correspondence and photocopied articles, 1983 - 1991
  - Miscellaneous (4) -- Mark Twain Drama and articles on Mark Twain, 1993 - 1995
  - Miscellaneous (5) -- Clipping and several 19th Century photocopied newspaper articles about Twain in Elmira, undated
  - Miscellaneous (6) -- Primarily Mark Twain promotional materials for Mark Twain events, includes photocopied research materials, 1982 - 1997
- Series 4: Research Files, 1907 - 1997
  This series is primarily comprised of research on Elmira persons with a Twain connection. The series is arranged alphabetically by author or subject.
  - Albright, Harriet Langdon (wife of John Joseph Albright) daughter of John LeDroit Langdon -- Notes, family tree, undated
  - Andrus, Sylvester -- Notes, undated
  - Barber, Julia Louise Langdon (Mrs. Amzi Lorenzo Barber) daughter of John Ledroit Langdon -- Correspondence and research materials, 1991 - 1994
  - Beecher, Thomas K. -- notes, photograph and letter transcriptions, undated
  - Brownell, Louise - Papers - friend of Susy Clemens, letter photocopies, undated
  - Clemens, Olivia Langdon -- Photocopied materials including Last Will and Testament, correspondence, clippings, "I am Woman's Rights: Olivia Langdon Clemens and her Feminist Circle" by Laura Skandera, 1986 - 1991
  - Clemens, Susy -- Photocopied newspaper articles, undated
  - Clemens, Susy -- Correspondence with Louis Brownell [photocopies] (1), undated
  - Clemens, Susy -- Correspondence with Louis Brownell [photocopies] (2), undated
  - Cord, Mary Ann (1798 - 1888) "Auntie Cord," -- Correspondence, clippings, research materials (photos of Aunite Cord to P:4:25), 1981 - 1994
  - Crane, Susan L. -- Notes, clippings and photocopied articles and newspaper clippings, 1977 - 1990
  - Crane, Theodore - Notes, Clippings, and articles, Crane Family photo of Theodore to MT:P:3:8, 1977
  - Darby, Dr. Frank W. -- Article from EC Report on donation of letters, 1993
  - Elmira Census Data -- Notes, undated
  - Elmira Lecturers -- Notes and research materials, undated
  - Elmira Photographers -- Notes and research materials, undated
  - Ely, Anson C. -- Notes and photocopied newspaper article, undated
  - Farrar, Charlie S. and family -- Notes, undated
  - Fausnaught, John -- Correspondence, photographs of John and Hartford home, notes, 1987
  - Fay, Cyrus W. -- "Mark Twain's tailor," article, notes and photocopied articles, undated
  - Ford, Andrew Jackson -- Notes, photocopied letters and MT Society Bulletin, Correspondence with Linda Owens, 1997
  - Ford, Darius R. -- Notes, photographs, undated
  - Ford, Eunice King & Langdon, Williams (grandma Ford) 1782-1873 -- Correspondence, geneaology, notes, and photocopied letters, includes photographs of the Ford Family, 1995 - 1996
  - Ford, John K. -- Notes, undated
  - Ford, Jonathan and family -- Notes, undated
  - Gabrilowitsch, Nina -- Materials from Mark Twain Papers, clipping, notes, 1993
  - Gleason, Rachel: The Watercure -- Notes, photocopied research materials, postcard, 1907
  - Halsey family - Sayles family -- Notes, undated
  - Holden, Anna Knight Beecher -- notes, correspondence, photocopied newsclippings, 1983
  - Ithaca and Enfield -- Property records, notes, correspondence, 1983
  - J. Langdon and co. -- Notes, photocopied article, undated
  - Koppe, G. Ernest (1868-1956) -- Photograph, manuscript for article in Mark Twain Society Bulletin and notes, undated
  - Langdon, Andrew -- Photograph from Buffalo and Erie Historical Society, 1992
  - Langdon, Charles J. -- Notes, transcription of letters, last will and testament, undated
  - Langdon, Ida (1880-1964) -- Photograph, notes, "Mark Twain's Neice: Ida Langdon," letters, photocopies, clippings, 1953 - 1964
  - Langdon, Ida Clark -- Notes, photocopied research materials, undated
  - Langdon, Jervis, 1809-1870 -- Notes, "Jervis Langdon: Christian Businessman" manuscript, photocopied letters and research materials, undated
  - Langdon, Jervis, 1875-1952 -- Notes, copy of will, clipping, photocopied materials, 1915
  - Langdon, Jervis, Jr. -- Clippings, photocopied news clippings, 1961 - 1998
  - Langdon, Jervis: Diaries -- Excerpts from diaries, notes, undated
  - Langdon, Jervis: Family library -- Letter from Stowe-Day Foundation and notes on books from Quarry Farm library, 1985
  - Langdon, Jervis: Family Library and Marginalia -- "Mark Twain on Petrarch: More Quarry Farm Marginalia," notes, photocopied materials, undated
  - Langdon, Jervis: House: 303 North Main, Elmira -- Notes, undated
  - Langdon, Jervis: Interviews -- "Jervis Langdon, Mark Twain's Father-In- Law"; manuscript and notes from interviews, 1985 - 1986
  - Langdon, John Ledroit -- Correspondence and notes, 1990
  - Langdon, Olivia Lewis -- Notes and photocopied news articles, undated
  - Langdon, Olivia Lewis: Diaries 1865-1867 -- Notes
  - Leary, Catherine (Katy) (1856-1934) -- Correspondence, notes, photographs from the dedication of Katy Leary Park in Elmira, clippings, 1990 - 1991
  - Lewis, John T. (1835-1906) -- Notes, MT Bulletin with Lewis article including the manuscript, article in the Messenger, 1985
  - Lewis Family -- Notes and photocopied letters, undated
  - Marsh family -- Correspondence, 1983
  - Dr. Norton - faith healer -- photocopied articles, undated
  - Noyes -- Notes, correspondence and photocopied articles, 1990
  - Nye, Emma -- "Tragic story of Emma Nye" manuscript, notes, photograph, photocopied articles, undated
  - Obituaries -- Notes and photocopied articles of various deaths in the Clemens/Langdon family, undated
  - Oneida and Madison Counties -- Photocopied materials, map, and notes concerning the area, 1989 - 1991
  - Paff, Harriett Lewis -- Reminiscences (Yale U. Library c. 1897), photocopied materials, undated
  - Palmer, Anna C. (Mrs. George Archibald & Georgianna) -- "Anna Palmer's Literary Legacy"; manuscript, notes and photocopied articles, undated
  - Park Church -- Centennial Album, notes, photocopied articles, 1975
  - Slee, J.D.F -- Correspondence concerning Slee, notes, 1989
  - Spaulding, Clara L. (1849-1935) (Mrs. John B. Stanchfield) -- Photograph, notes and photocopied letters, 1987
  - Thurston, Miss Clarissa. Elmira Seminary -- Notes, photocopied articles, undated
  - Van Aken, Elisha M. (1828-1904) and son Charles (1865-1952) Elmira photographers -- photograph, photocopied articles and correspondence concerning gift of letter to Elmira College, 1986